Okay, so the first programmatic assessment was .value_counts on
حسنًا، كان أول تقييم برمجي .value_counts في
the surname and address column at the patient's table.
عمود العنوان واللقب في جدول المرضى.
Value counts is like a histogramming function
تشبه أعداد القيمة دالة رسم المدرج التكراري
that returns the count of each unique value in that column.
التي ترجع عدد كل قيمة فريدة في هذا العمود.
And there are six last names of Doe as well as six addresses of 123 Main Street.
هناك ستة أسماء عائلة لـ Doe وستة عناوين بهذا العنوان 123 Main Street.
I've got a hunch that these are duplicates which we can check using .duplicated.
لقد أدركت وجود تكرارات يمكننا التحقق منها باستخدام .duplicated.
This returns a boolean series which we then index patients with.
إذ أنها ترجع سلسلة منطقية نقوم بفهرسة المرضى فيها.
And, yeah, there are several John Doe's that live at 123 Main Street New York,
أجل، يوجد عدة أشخاص باسم John Doe الذي يعيش في نفس العنوان 123 Main Street New York،
New York, ZIP Code 12345.
New York، الرمز البريدي 12345.
And there's more, johndoe@email.com.
ويوجد أكثر من ذلك، johndoe@email.com.
This reeks of duplicate default data.
نتج ذلك من البيانات الافتراضية المكررة.
So how could this have happened.
حسنًا، كيف حدث هذا.
This is probably because of some system conversion.
ربما يحدث ذلك بسبب بعض أعمال تحويل النظام.
For example, say if the company that has
على سبيل المثال، لنفترض ما إذا كانت الشركة
this database switched from one software provider to another for their patient records.
التي تحتوي على قاعدة البيانات هذه قد تحولت من مزود برامج إلى آخر لتسجيل سجلات المرضى الخاصة بها.
When converting from one system to another,
عند التحويل من نظام إلى آخر،
you can often lose data and it becomes this default John Doe data or even corrupted data.
غالبًا ما ستفقدون البيانات وتصبح بيانات John Doe الافتراضية هذه أو بيانات تالفة حتى.
This is a pretty common issue in health care data,
هذه مشكلة شائعة جدًا في بيانات الرعاية الصحية،
especially because healthcare is known as not
لا سيما أن الرعاية الصحية تُعرف بأنها
being the most up-to-date in terms of technology.
ليست الأكثر تحديثًا من حيث التكنولوجيا.
So what's the appropriate data quality dimension for this one.
حسنًا ما هو البعد المناسب لجودة البيانات لذلك.
This is a validity issue.
هذه مشكلة التحقق.
Recall that validity means not conforming to
تذكر أن التحقق يعني عدم التطابق
a defined schema and this schema is the real world schema this time.
مع مخطط محدد وهذا المخطط هو مخطط العالم الواقعي هذه المرة.
It's very, very, very unlikely,
من المستبعد جدًا،
I'd say impossible that there are six
بل من المستحيل أن يكون هناك ستة أشخاص
John Doe's that all live at 123 Main Street in New York,
باسم John Doe يعيشون جميعًا في هذا العنوان 123 Main Street in New York،
New York with the same email.
New York بالبريد الإلكتروني نفسه.
It's just not, this isn't happening.
لا يمكن أن يحدث مثل هذا الأمر.
So while this table or the database accepts these records,
لذا، في حين أن هذا الجدول أو قاعدة البيانات يقبل هذه السجلات،
it's not valid in terms of the real world schema.
فإنه لا ينطبق على مخطط العالم الواقعي.
John Doe might not even exist and realistically he probably doesn't.
ربما لا يكون John Doe موجودًا، وفي الواقع ربما لا يكون موجودًا.
So let's document that.
حسنًا لنوثق ذلك.
It'll be important to clean this because we don't want garbage data in our data set.
سيكون من المهم تنظيف ذلك لأننا لن نرغب في إدخال بيانات تالفة في مجموعة البيانات.
This might mean removing these records or finding records that were lost,
قد يعني هذا إزالة هذه السجلات أو العثور على السجلات التي فقدت،
but we'll deal with that later.
ولكننا سنتعامل معها لاحقًا.
Right now we're just assessing and writing down our observations.
أما الآن سنقوم بتقييم الملاحظات وندونها فقط.
There's actually another data quality issue revealed by
في الواقع، هناك مشكلة أخرى في جودة البيانات تم الكشف عنها
this duplicated method here and one offending record is this Jake Jacobson record.
بهذه الطريقة المكررة هنا وهي وجود سجل واحد مسيء هو سجل Jake Jacobson.
You'll see that this duplicate actually has
سترى أن هذا التكرار يحتوي بالفعل على
address being duplicated as opposed to this record here,
عنوان يتكرر بدلًا من هذا السجل هنا،
or these two down here having NaN entries.
أو هذين العنوانين اللذين يوجد بهما إدخالات NaN.
This means that two people in this patient's table have the same address,
يعني ذلك أن هناك شخصان في جدول المرضى هذا لهما نفس العنوان،
648 Old Dear Lane.
648 Old Dear Lane.
I actually recall seeing
أتذكر حقًا أنني رأيت
a Jacobson earlier in our visual assessment. Let's scroll back up.
Jacobson في وقت سابق في التقييم البصري. لنقم بالتمرير لأعلى مرة أخرى.
Okay, here it is, Jacob Jacobson,
حسنًا، هذا هو Jacob Jacobson،
648 Old Dear Lane and also a Jake Jacobson,
648 Old Dear Lane ويوجد أيضًا Jake Jacobson،
which is a record we saw in the duplicated results below.
وهو السجل الذي رأيناه في النتائج المكررة أدناه.
So this seems like there's two records for one person.
حسنًا، يبدو أنه يوجد سجلان لشخص واحد.
This extra record and extra patient ID was created because this nickname was used.
تم إنشاء هذا السجل الإضافي ومعرِّف المريض الإضافي بسبب استخدام هذا اللقب.
Basically Jake Jacobson came back twice and the person that was in charge of creating
في الأساس عاد Jake Jacobson مرتين وسجل الشخص المسؤول عن إنشاء
these patient records accidentally put Jake in again
هذه السجلات الخاصة بالمريض Jake مرة أخرى دون قصد
because they didn't recognize that he was already in the database.
لأنهم لم يدركوا أنه موجود بالفعل في قاعدة البيانات.
This use of nicknames creating duplicates is a very famous issue in
استخدام الألقاب هذه الذي ينشئ تكرارًا هو مشكلة مشهورة جدًا
healthcare data and it's an issue that costs
في بيانات الرعاية الصحية، وهي مشكلة
healthcare companies and hospitals tons of money every year.
تكلف شركات الرعاية الصحية والمستشفيات الكثير من المال كل عام.
There's a handy link illustrating this in the notes below
تجدون رابطًا مفيدًا يوضح ذلك في الملاحظات أسفل
this video if you'd like to read more.
هذا الفيديو إذا أردتم معرفة المزيد.
So this is actually a validity issue currently.
لذا إنها مشكلة التحقق حاليًا.
Though it's pretty easy to confuse as a consistency issue.
على الرغم من أنه من السهل جدًا الارتباك لأنها مشكلة تناسق.
Consistency being two ways of referring to the same thing,
التناسق هو طريقتان للإشارة إلى الشيء نفسه،
Jake and Jacob Jacobson.
Jake وJacob Jacobson.
So while this is valid in terms of the specific table schema,
وإذا كان ذلك صالحًا في مخطط الجدول المحدد،
there's no duplicate patient ID i.e.
فلا يوجد معرف مريض مكرر، بمعنى
Jake Jacobson has 30,
أن معرف Jake Jacobson هو 30،
Jacob has 25 for patient ID.
بينما معرف Jacob هو 25.
But this is invalid in terms of the real world schema.
ويكون ذلك غير صالح في مخطط العالم الواقعي.
This isn't two people, it's one person.
فلا يشير ذلك إلى شخصين، إنما إلى شخص واحد.
There are two records in the patients table while there should be one.
يوجد سجلان في جدول المرضى في حين ينبغي أن يكون هناك سجل واحد.
When deleting one of the duplicates,
عند حذف أحد التكرارات،
if we delete the wrong one,
إذا حذفتم التكرار الخطأ،
then we'll create a consistency issue between multiple tables.
فسننشئ مشكلة تناسق بين عدة جداول.
For example, if Jacob Jacobson is in the treatments table as well while
على سبيل المثال، إذا كان Jacob Jacobson موجودًا في جدول العلاجات أيضًا
this Jake Jacobson is only in patients and we delete the Jacob Jacobson record,
في حين أن Jake Jacobson يكون في جدول المرضى فقط ونحذف سجل Jacob Jacobson،
that would be a inconsistent representation across tables,
فسيكون هذا تمثيلًا غير متناسق عبر الجداول،
while still having only one record per one person,
بينما لا يزال هناك سجل واحد لكل شخص واحد فقط،
so it's valid but inconsistent.
لذا يكون ذلك صالحًا ولكن غير متناسق.
That's not what we have right now though.
ومع ذلك، لا نتطرق إلى ذلك الآن.
Right now we have two ways of referring to
نتطرق الآن إلى طريقتين للإشارة إلى
two records when there should only be one record.
سجلين عندما ينبغي وجود سجل واحد فقط.
That last part is the invalid part.
هذا الجزء الأخير هو الجزء غير الصالح.
There are actually a few more of these nickname duplicated patients.
يوجد حقًا عدد قليل آخر من المرض الذين تم تكرارهم بألقاب.
Sandy Taylor and Sandra Taylor,
Sandy Taylor وSandra Taylor،
living at 2476 Fulton Street.
تعيش في 2476 Fulton Street.
Then also Pat and Patrick Gersten that lives at 2778 North Avenue.
ويوجد أيضًا Pat وPatrick Gersten اللذان يعيشان في 2778 North Avenue.
And as always we document this.
وكالعادة نقوم بتوثيق ذلك.
Okay, so let's move on to the next programmatic assessment
حسنًا، لننتقل إلى التقييم البرمجي التالي
on the weight column in the patient's table.
في عمود الوزن في جدول المرضى.
And the minimum value is 48.8 pounds.
أدنى قيمة هي 48.8 رطلًا.
This seems not possible for a living human,
ويبدو ذلك غير ممكن للإنسان الحي،
so this is definitely at least inaccurate, maybe invalid.
لذا فإنه بالتأكيد غير دقيق، وربما ليس صالحًا.
But actually if we think a bit deeper,
لكن في الواقع، إذا فكرنا أكثر،
we'll see that it's actually neither of those.
فسنرى أنه حقًا لا يرجع إلى تلك الأمور.
This is actually a consistency issue in disguise.
إنها في الواقع تكمن في مشكلة تناسق.
48.8 is actually kilograms instead of pounds,
48.8 تكون بالكيلو جرام وليس بالرطل،
which we can check by corroborating the height and
وهذا الأمر يمكن التحقق منه عن طريق توثيق إدخالات الطول
BMI entries for this patient who has the last name Zaitseva.
ومؤشر كتلة الجسم للمريض الذي يكون اسم عائلته Zaitseva.
So 2.20462 is the conversion factor between kilograms and pounds
لذا إن 2.20462 هو عامل تحويل بين الكيلوجرام والرطل
and 703 times weight in pounds divided by height squared is the BMI calculation formula.
و703 مضروبًا في الوزن بالرطل مقسومًا على الطول المربع هو صيغة حساب مؤشر كتلة الجسم.
And with 48.8 kilograms converted to pounds,
بتحويل 48.8 كيلو جرامًا إلى الأرطال،
this yields about 19.1 BMI,
فإن هذا ينتج مؤشر كتلة جسم حوالي 19.1،
which if we checked the actual BMI in the data set is
وهو ما إذا تحققنا من أن مؤشر كتلة الجسم الفعلي في مجموعة البيانات
exactly the same or close to it before rounding.
هي نفس القيمة السابقة تمامًا أو قريبة منها قبل التقريب.
So here the 48.8 is actually right,
إذًا إن 48.8 قيمة صحيحة حقًا،
it's just off in units.
إنما المشكلة تكمن في الوحدات.
So this is actually a consistency issue.
إنها مشكلة تناسق حقًا.
This was caused by a simple misunderstanding or
ونتج هذا عن سوء فهم بسيط
just a simple oversight by whoever was entering this data.
أو مراقبة بسيطة من قِبل أي شخص كان يدخل هذه البيانات.
Again, this is important to clean because we need to report the average metrics,
مرة أخرى، عملية التنظيف مهمة جدًا لأننا نحتاج إلى الإبلاغ عن متوسط المقاييس،
like weight, height, and more,
مثل الوزن والطول وغير ذلك،
in terms of each treatment arm of the clinical trial.
من حيث كل ذراع معالجة للتجربة الإكلينيكية.
Auralin and Novodra and there's some documentation for this.
Auralin وNovodra وهناك بعض الوثائق لهذا.
And Okay now the last programmatic assessments,
حسنًا، نتطرق الآن إلى التقييم البرمجي الأخير،
the .isnull methods on the Auralin and Novodra columns in the treatment's table.
أساليب .isnull في أعمدة Auralin وNovodra في جدول العلاجات.
This bit of code within the sum parentheses.
هذا الجزء الصغير من الكود يوجد في أقواس sum.
This returns a Boolean series which is
يرجع ذلك سلسلة منطقية
true or false based on whether or not each entry is null or not.
تكون صحيحة أو خطأ اعتمادًا على ما إذا كان كل إدخال يحتوي على قيمة فارغة أم لا.
And Boolean series can be summed as a whole.
يمكن جمع السلسلة المنطقية كوحدة كاملة.
True being one, false being zero.
القيمة واحد صحيحة، والقيمة صفر خطأ.
So this output suggests that there are
لذا تشير هذه النتيجة إلى وجود
zero null entries for both the Auralin and Novodra columns.
إدخالات فارغة بقيمة صفر في كلٍّ من عمودي Auralin وNovodra.
But that shouldn't be the case, right?
لكن لا يجب أن يكون هذا الأمر كذلك، أليس كذلك؟
If we scroll up to our treatment's visual assessment,
إذا مررنا إلى الأعلى إلى التقييم البصري للعلاج،
these entries with the dashes should be null or at least represented as such.
يجب أن تكون هذه الإدخالات التي تحتوي على الشرطات خالية أو ممثلة بذلك على الأقل.
This reveals a common error in multiple data sets,
يكشف ذلك عن خطأ شائع في مجموعات البيانات المتعددة،
not just healthcare data sets.
وليس في مجموعات بيانات الرعاية الصحية فقط.
Misrepresenting missing values is something else,
سوء تمثيل القيم المفقودة مشكلة أخرى،
like a dash or a slash or NaN
مثل شرطة أو شرطة مائلة أو NaN
or none for example, the text None.
أو لا شيء، على سبيل المثال، النص غير موجود.
And if you scroll down to our info programmatic assessment,
إذا مررتم إلى الأسفل إلى التقييم البرمجي،
the Auralin and Novodra columns are objects or strings.
فإن أعمدة Auralin وNovodra هي كائنات أو سلاسل.
These dashes aren't picked up as null or non-values.
ولا يتم فهم هذه الشرطات على أنها قيم فارغة أو عدم وجود قيم.
Why is this important to document and later clean?
لماذا يكون ذلك مهمًا لإجراء عملية التوثيق والتنظيف فيما بعد؟
Calculations in Pandas and spreadsheet applications even behave
تتبع الحسابات في تطبيقات جدول البيانات وPandas
a certain way based on how these null values are represented.
طريقة معينة تعتمد على كيفية تمثيل هذه القيم الخالية.
In Pandas for example,
ففي Pandas على سبيل المثال،
since each column or series can only have one data type,
نظرًا لأن كل عمود أو سلسلة لا يمكن أن يحتوي إلا على نوع بيانات واحد فقط،
we wouldn't be able to convert these dosage columns to
فإننا لن نتمكن من تحويل أعمدة الجرعة هذه
a numerical data type to perform mean and standard deviation calculations,
إلى نوع بيانات رقمي لإجراء حسابات الانحراف المعياري والمتوسط،
which we'll need to report in the clinical trial findings.
والتي سنحتاج إلى الإبلاغ عنها في نتائج التجارب الإكلينيكية.
But also nulls are important.
لكن القيم الخالية مهمة أيضًا.
Again, if you're working in something like Google Sheets or a spreadsheet application.
مرة أخرى، إذا كنتم تعملون في تطبيق ما مثل Google Sheets أو تطبيق جدول البيانات.
So spreadsheet applications allow multiple data types in one column,
تسمح تطبيقات جدول البيانات بإدخال عدة أنواع بيانات في عمود واحد،
like this is allowed 40-50 dash dash dash 60.
مثل مسموح بذلك 40-50 شرطة شرطة شرطة 60.
With this cell this cell and this cell 40-50-60 still being treated as
في هذه الخلية وهذه وذلك، 40-50-60 لا تزال تعامل على
integers while these dash dash dash cells are treated as text variables.
أنها أعداد صحيحة بينما تُعالج هذه الخلايا التي تحتوي على شرطة شرطة شرطة على أنها متغيرات نصية.
This is important because say if you wanted to
هذه مهم جدًا لأنكم إذا أردتم
calculate standard deviation for this column,
حساب الانحراف المعياري لهذا العمود،
this example column, the function STDEVA.
هذا العمود مثلًا، دالة STDEVA.
This calculates standard deviation but sets the text
إنها تحسب الانحراف المعياري لكنها تعيّن القيم النصية
values aka the dash dash dash to zero.
التي تُعرف أيضًا باسم شرطة شرطة شرطة على صفر.
If these were missing values you'd get a different calculation,
إذا كانت هذه قيم مفقودة، فستحصلون على حساب مختلف،
which I'll show you right here actually.
والذي سأريكم إياه هنا في الواقع.
So the correct representation of nulls is important.
حسنًا، إن التمثيل الصحيح للقيم الخالية أمر مهم.
So let's document that.
حسنًا لنوثق ذلك.
This is a validity issue because nulls should be nulls, not text
إنها مشكلة تحقق لأن القيم الخالية يجب أن تكون خالية وليست نصًا